Guide to the Lesotho Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lesotho collection
1904-2012
MS 1524
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.02
(11 boxes)
The collection consists of reports, speeches, and printed material relating to the history of Lesotho and the current political, economic, and social conditions. Photographs are also included.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); Pamphlet Collection (MS 1351); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of reports, speeches, and printed material relating to the history of Lesotho and the current political, economic, and social conditions. Photographs are also included.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ecology -- Lesotho; Education -- Lesotho; Lesotho -- Description and travel; Lesotho -- Economic conditions; Lesotho -- Politics and government; Lesotho -- Social conditions; United Nations -- Lesotho
- Inventory, 1904-1994
  - "Naledi Ea Lesotho - Basutoland Star": newspaper, 1904-1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, [1961?]-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government documents; journals; reports, 1964-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, 1966-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lesotho - the Politics of Dependence, by J. E. Spence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Political organizations: printed material, 1970-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Speeches by government officials, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anniversary of Independence: Sixth, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anniversary of Independence: Seventh, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Moshoeshoe II: "Birthday celebrations", 1972 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Leabua Jonathan - a Tribute to the Prime Minister of the Kingdom of Lesotho", 1972 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rural and urban development and environmental concerns, 1973-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Leselinyana La Lesotho": editorials, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Social science research, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Journals: social; economic; military; educational, 1976-1992, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Political organizations: printed material, 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The National University of Lesotho: printed material, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Lesotho National Development Corporation: journals, newsletters, portfolios, 1980-1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Transformation Resource Center: "Work for Justice"; news bulletins, 1984-1993 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Puo Ea Motlotlehi Moshoeshoe II Mohla Letsatsi La Sesole-Maseru", 1987 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Origins and Growth of Maseru: report prepared by David Ambrose, National University of Lesotho, for the Department of Lands, Surveys and Physical Planning, [1993]-1994
    - "From Earliest Times to1905": volume 1A (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "From 1905 to 1991": volume1B (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Aerial Photographs and Appendices": volume 2 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Chronology of Important Events in the History ofMaseru": volume 3 and updates (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Vernacular Lesotho press, description of: letter to Moore Crossey from David Ambrose at National University of Lesotho, 1993 September (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Additional Material, 1979-1997; Accession 1995-M-148
  - Additional printed materials, 1979, 1988-1997, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1879-1998; Accession 1999-M-013
  - Additional printed materials, 1879, 1926, 1937, 1945, 1954, 1966, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1993-1998; Accession 2000-M-023
  - Additional printed materials [includes 1998 election materials], 1993, 1996, 1998 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1960-2002; Accession 2004-M-041
  - "Clarion" [National University of Lesotho student publication; vol. 5, no. 1], [1983?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Booklets [political parties: BNP, KBP, LCD, LPC, NIP, PFD, SDP], 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Booklets [women, birth control, domestic violence, rape], 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Independent Electoral Commission (IEC) [flyers,booklets], 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous [Maseru United Church history, Thaba Bosiu National Monument pamphlet], 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs [daily life, Pius XII College, historic cemetery, miscellaneous], 1960-1971, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Souvenir Album: 25 Choice Views of Basutoland, the Switzerland of South-Africa", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, 1957-2004; Accession 2006-M-035
  - Appropriate Technology Section (ATS) "Tin/Can Fireplace", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committee for Action and Solidarity for Southern African Students (CASSAS), "The Vanguard," vol. 4, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ireland Aid Primary Schools Construction Project in Lesotho, "I Like My School...I Really Do", [2004] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lesotho Highlands Development Authority, "Liposto le Likarabo", [1998] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Litaba tsa Lesotho", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mohale Schools Health and Environment Club (SHE), "Rata Tikoloho Ea Hau Joalokaha U Ithata", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mohlabani, vol. 3, nos. 1-4, 1957 April (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National University of Lesotho (NUL), "Lehlaahlela", 1991 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Office of the Ombudsman, "Special Report in the Matter of Complaints by the Resettled People Against the Lesotho Highlands Development Authority", 2003 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Privatisation Unit
    - "Privatisation Progress in Lesotho", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Lesotho Privatisation and Private Sector Development Project", 2002 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Svenskarnas Info Blad Newsletter", 1991 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thebe, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Treasury Echo," vol.2, no. 4, vol. 4, nos. 1-3, 1991 April, 1993 Jul, Dec, 1994 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - UNICEF, "Children Have Rights Too" bilingual booklet, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Additional Material, 1955-2005; Accession 2010-M-108
  Arrangement
  The material is arranged as received.
  - Preservation and promotion of Sephuthi language (printout), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - St. James High School (MKG) Celebrates 50th Anniversary, 1955-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mosebetsi Ithute, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lesotho Population Data Sheet, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lesotho Members of National Assembly poster, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1975-2012; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1975-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, 2001-2009 (Folder 2)